<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached before the King on Easter-Day, 1684 by Francis Lord Bishop of Rochester ...</title>
            <author>Turner, Francis, 1638?-1700.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1684</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 46 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A63882</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T3283</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R38918</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">18189464</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 18189464</idno>
            <idno type="VID">106985</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A63882)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 106985)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1133:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached before the King on Easter-Day, 1684 by Francis Lord Bishop of Rochester ...</title>
                  <author>Turner, Francis, 1638?-1700.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 33 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J. Macock for R. Royston...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1684.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Published by His Majesties Special Command."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Hosea VI, 2-3 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:106985:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached before the KING, On <hi>Eaſter-Day,</hi> 1684.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Francis</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Rocheſter,</hi> and ALMONER to His MAJESTY.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed by his Majeſties ſpecial Command.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. Macock</hi> for <hi>R. Royſton</hi> Book-ſeller to His moſt Sacred Majeſty, at the <hi>Angel</hi> in <hi>Amen-Corner,</hi> 1684.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:106985:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:106985:2"/>
                  <bibl>Hoſea VI. 2, 3.</bibl>
                  <p>After two days will He revive us, in the third day He will raiſe us up, and we ſhall live in his ſight.</p>
                  <p>Then ſhall we know, if we follow on to know the Lord: his going forth is prepared as the morning; and He ſhall come unto us as the rain; as the latter and former rain unto the earth.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>SUCH an Auguſt and Solemn Aſſembly as this, how well does it ſuit with thoſe Glorious, Titles the Ancient Fathers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow upon Eaſter-Day, <hi>the Feaſt of Feaſts, the Solemnity of Solemnities, the</hi> Queen <hi>or</hi> Empreſs <hi>of all the Churches</hi> Feſtivals! And well may the Chriſtian Church be allowed to pay the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt obſervance and greateſt reverence to the memory of his Reſurrection, <hi>Whom God hath raiſed up to be a Prince, and a Saviour,</hi> (as St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſtyles Him) <hi>to be our God, and our Lord</hi> (as Saint <hi>Thomas</hi> calls him); when even the Gentile World, whom ever they took upon them to worſhip as a God, their natural Religion di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctated to them this, That Feaſts in Honour of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:106985:3"/> Him ſhould be obſerved. The Roman Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour <hi>Tiberius</hi> (as <hi>Euſebius</hi> relates) upon that amazing Story he received from his Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant <hi>Pontius Pilate,</hi> concerning our Saviours Death and Reſurrection, was very deſirous to have Deified our Lord Chriſt: But by the ſpecial Providence of God, the Senate found a pretence to croſs that Deſign of <hi>Tiberius;</hi> for Chriſt would never be beholding to the Secular Heathen Powers to advance his Divinity, which was to aſtoniſh the World into its belief by a quite contrary method, of ſuffering their Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions, and dying for it.</p>
            <p>But ſince all the Triumphs of Chriſt, that were the conſequence of his Death and Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, began from his Reſurrection, <hi>(Becauſe he was obedient unto death, even the death upon the Croſs, therefore God alſo hath highly exalted him;</hi> again, <hi>God hath made that ſame Jeſus, whom ye have crucified, both Lord and Chriſt;</hi> which implies, that Chriſt was made more <hi>The Chriſt,</hi> that is, more <hi>The Anointed Son of God,</hi> by his being <hi>the firſt-begotten from the dead</hi> this Day;) then we muſt needs allow this Day a preference to all others in our Chriſtian Calendar: This is foretold, <hi>As the Day of his Power, when the people ſhould offer him free-will Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings with an holy worſhip;</hi> when he was firſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:106985:3"/> to declare, <hi>All power is given unto me in Heaven and earth;</hi> This is the Day which Chriſt has call'd properly <hi>His, Father Abraham deſired to ſee my Day, and he ſaw it, and was glad to ſee it,</hi> then when he <hi>received, Iſaac from the dead in a Figure,</hi> a Type of Chriſt. <hi>This is the Day which the Lord hath made:</hi> I could alledge a great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the Antients interpreting that Paſſage of the Pſalmiſt, as Prophetical of Eaſter-Day; a Feſtival that we hear of in as old a Record, and as venerable a Piece of Antiquity, as is the Story of <hi>Polycarp,</hi> St. <hi>John</hi>'s Diſciple; a Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtival, which <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> the firſt Great Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Emperour, commanded by a ſpecial E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict to be obſerved; which <hi>Socrates</hi> our Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Hiſtorian aſſures us, that in his time no Hereticks had impudence enough to diſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, nay, that all of them kept it. Now me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks 'tis exceeding ſtrange, that ſo many of our Schiſmaticks ſhould have ſo much zeal as they pretend to have for the Weekly Feſtival, and none for the Annual Commemoration of our Bleſſed Lords Reſurrection; that the Lords Day being confeſſedly derived from this Day, every Sunday but as a ſhadow of Eaſter: Yet ſome almoſt Judaizing in the Doctrine of the Sabbath, ſhould refuſe to join with the reſt of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:106985:4"/> the Chriſtian World in honouring of this Day, whence the other one and fifty Days in the Year had all their beginning, and borrow all their Glory. But as for you that come hither on the ſcore of Devotion, I may addreſs my ſelf to you, as the Angel began to thoſe that had the honour to hear the firſt welcome News of this Day, <hi>Ye ſeek Jeſus of Nazareth, that was crucified; He is riſen.</hi> The Chriſtian Saints of old, when they met upon Eaſter-Morning, the one accoſted the other with this Salutation, <hi>Chriſt is riſen;</hi> the Cuſtom ſtill continues in the Greek Churches, to which the other joyfully echoes and replies, <hi>Yes, Chriſt is riſen:</hi> But I will not ſay with the Angel, <hi>Ye ſeek Jeſus, He is not here;</hi> Indeed he was no longer there in his Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but he is here in the Bleſſed Sacrament, which ſhall be in the worthy Receivers as, <hi>Seeds of the Reſurrection,</hi> ('tis <hi>Irenaeus</hi>'s expreſſion) <hi>to make our vile Bodies like his glorious Body;</hi> and he is here in the Text, as I ſhall clearly ſhew, though it were but an obſcure Prophecy to the Jews, as every Prophecy is a Myſtery till it be fulfilled; yet now 'tis turn'd into the plain Story of this time; to us Chriſtians 'tis a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration, if it pleaſes Chriſt <hi>to open our hearts,</hi> as he did thoſe of the two Diſciples that went
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:106985:4"/> to <hi>Emmaus, when he expounded unto them in all the Scriptures, and all the Prophets, the things concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf, That Chriſt ought to have ſuffered thoſe things, and to enter into his Glory:</hi> for unleſs he <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen our eyes,</hi> as he did theirs <hi>while he opened the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures to them,</hi> we may be but as they were, <hi>ſlow of heart to believe all that the Prophets have ſpoken.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> who tells ſome parts of this Story concerning the Reſurrection more pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually than even the Goſpels have done, tells us, that <hi>Chriſt roſe the third Day, according to the Scriptures.</hi> The Reſurrection is the only Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of our Creed that has the circumſtance of time particularly annexed to it; and this he ſays <hi>was according to the Scriptures, that Chriſt roſe the third Day:</hi> Which are thoſe Scriptures then? For he muſt needs mean thoſe in the Old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament; and which are thoſe? None more plain than this place of <hi>Hoſea;</hi> which therefore I have choſen to diſcourſe upon, though it be not ſo commonly obſerved, and though it be left for an exerciſe of our Chriſtian Induſtry, which ſhould be much employ'd <hi>in ſearching the Scriptures,</hi> for this is a Text not quoted in any place of the New Teſtament: Yet I ſhall not deny, but this Prophecy might alſo ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:106985:5"/> that <hi>reviving</hi> or reſtoring of Gods people from their woful Captivity, in which they were, as it were, <hi>dead men and dry bones,</hi> (as the Prophet <hi>Ezekiel</hi> calls them;) Recovering their Liberty was like receiving new life, after <hi>thoſe two days,</hi> or two calamitous times, firſt of the Aſſyrian Captivity, then of the Babylonian; and then a third glorious Day broke out joyful and happy to them, upon the Victories and Triumphs of the Great <hi>Cyrus,</hi> (whom the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> calls by his Name ſome Ages before he was born, <hi>Who hath ſaid unto Cyrus, Thou art my Shepherd);</hi> accordingly <hi>Cyrus</hi> took or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der for <hi>gathering the ſcattered ſheep of Iſrael,</hi> for raiſing them up from a kind of Civil Death, from Slavery to Freedom, from Baniſhment to reſettle them in their own Country. But al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing this Interpretation of the Text in its firſt literal meaning, it does not follow but a higher ſenſe ſhould be put upon the words; the Fathers and learned Antients contend with one voice, that <hi>Chriſt is here,</hi> that his plenteous Redemption, his gracious releaſing us from the Death of ſin, his raiſing us to the Life of Grace, of Righteouſneſs and of Glory, were prefigured and typified by that reſtauration and temporal deliverance of the Jews: 'Tis
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:106985:5"/> Chriſt, whoſe <hi>going forth from the boſome of the Father</hi> into the World, is ſaid in my Text <hi>to be prepared as the Morning,</hi> prepared of God by his ever-fixt and never-failing Decree; by the <hi>determinate counſel and foreknowledge</hi> of God, the very Days of Chriſt's Incarnation, his Birth, and his Reſurrection, were appointed ſet-days, as certain to come, as they were ſurely expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>thoſe that waited for the conſolation of Iſrael,</hi> who ſhould no more be diſappointed in their expectation, than thoſe that lookt for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant returns of the Morning-light; and this Day of his was to be <hi>as the Morning, as the Day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring from on high,</hi> to diſpel the darkneſs by the preſence of his Light; to diſperſe the Fumes, that from ignorance and ſin, with its mortal effects, had ſo long clouded the minds of men; to dilate and ſpread over all the World the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence of his heavenly Doctrine, both of Grace and Glory: and as he is likened to <hi>the Light,</hi> ſo he is alſo ſet forth in my Text by that other great Bleſſing from Heaven upon Earth, <hi>the Rain, And he ſhall come unto us as the Rain;</hi> ſo ſays the Pſalmiſt, <hi>He ſhall come down like the Rain in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Fleece of Wool,</hi> ſo gentle, ſo refreſhing, and ſo fructifying, <hi>even as the drops that water the earth;</hi> an Emblem of Chriſt that <hi>Iſaiah</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:106985:6"/> to uſe, <hi>Drop down ye heavens from above, and let the skies pour down righteouſneſs.</hi> But there is ſomething more implied in his <hi>Coming unto us as the latter and former rain unto the earth:</hi> For in that part of the Earth, the Holy Land, that <hi>flow'd with milk and honey,</hi> it was one of their Bleſſings, that theſe Rains came at ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times and ſeaſons, not ſo uncertainly as in theſe Parts of the World; but the <hi>former rain</hi> about the time of <hi>ſowing their Seed,</hi> the <hi>latter rain</hi> about this very time, in the Spring: And if Chriſt be there compared to that former Autumnal, and this latter Eaſter Rain, 'tis eaſie from our own thoughts to draw out the parallel, That He came <hi>like the former Rain</hi> at his holy Nativi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and <hi>like the latter Rain</hi> at his new Birth, for ſo His Reſurrection is called and thus compared, as well as His Eternal Generation, <hi>The Dew of thy Birth is as the Womb of the Morning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Words being thus explain'd, I may proſecute the Deſign of them either of theſe two ways, as there are two methods of hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling any Article of the Chriſtian Faith: for Example, this of the Reſurrection may be treated of, either, firſt, in an Hiſtorical way, conſidering the Matter of Fact it ſelf that makes up the Article; ſo in my Text this Matter of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:106985:6"/> Fact is ſuppoſed, that Chriſt revived after two days, or was rais'd up again the third day.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The Article may be enquired in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, as it is a Myſtery of Faith, or as it contains the Effects, the conſequence of theſe great things that Chriſt either acted or ſuffered for us, ſo the power of his Reſurrection (as St. <hi>Paul</hi> calls it) is alſo ſet down in theſe words, <hi>He ſhall revive us, He ſhall raiſe us up again, and we ſhall live in his ſight: He ſhall come unto us as the rain, as the latter and former rain unto the earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But thirdly, Here is an Obligation upon our parts, or a Condition impoſed upon us: if we mean to reap advantage from this revealed Doctrine of Chriſt's Reſurrection and ours; then muſt theſe Principles be purſued extreme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly home, and we muſt go on throughout the whole courſe of our lives to practiſe according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>Then ſhall we know, if we follow on to know the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt then I ſhall conſider the Matter of Fact that makes up the Article of Faith, as it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in this glorious Prophecy, and in ſome others like it. For <hi>the teſtimony of Jeſus is the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Prophecy,</hi> ſays St. <hi>John</hi> the Apoſtle; and it was a great and juſt Appeal that the Prophet
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:106985:7"/> 
               <hi>Iſaiah</hi> made againſt Idols, and their falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, <hi>Shew the things that are to come hereafter, that we may know that ye are Gods.</hi> Now if ever things to come were plainly and diſtinctly ſhewed long before, theſe ſo important Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actions relating to our Saviours Paſſion and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection were written as with a Sun-Beam, were tranſlated out of Hebrew into Greek by the Command of a Heathen Prince, but by Gods ſpecial Providence, ſome Ages before their Completion; Whoſe voice could it be, if not his that was before <hi>David,</hi> who ſpake it in his behalf, <hi>They pierced my hands and my feet?</hi> Who was ſo pierced, but he, with the Nails on his Croſs? <hi>I may tell all my Bones,</hi> as it follows there: Could there be a more proper deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption of that Diſtortion he ſuffered during his Extenſion upon the curſed Tree? 'Tis as na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally painted out in <hi>Iſai.</hi> 25. another of the four Evangeliſts, (as I may call the four Great Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets) of the Old Teſtament <hi>And he ſhall ſpread forth his hands in the midſt of them, as he that ſwim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, ſpreadeth forth his hands to ſwim;</hi> that the very Price ſhould be ſet down beforehand, the <hi>good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly price at which they valu'd him,</hi> and what they ſhould do with it, <hi>Buy the Field of Bloud;</hi> then that every circumſtance of his Death ſhould be
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:106985:7"/> ſo punctually foretold, the very words they ſhould contemptuouſly ſpeak in the midſt of his Paſſion, <hi>He truſted in God that he would deliver him; let him deliver him, if he will have him.</hi> The words ſtood a long time before, where they ſtand now, in the <hi>22th</hi> Pſalm, the Paſſion-Pſalm; there you may alſo find <hi>the Souldiers parting his Garments among them, and caſting lots for his ſeemleſs Coat:</hi> It looks more like a Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry than a Prophecy; yet <hi>Greece</hi> from the <hi>Septua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gint</hi> atteſts the words, as well as does <hi>Judaea</hi> from the Original. <hi>That there ſhould be darkneſs over the earth,</hi> and the Sun ſhould not give its light; they had warning of it, <hi>Amos</hi> 8. 9. <hi>And it ſhall come to paſs in that day, ſaith the Lord God, that I will cauſe the Sun to go down at Noon, and I will dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the earth in the clear day.</hi> Why, there were many Eclipſes, ſay the Jews: Not one, by their good favour, when the Moon was at Full, as it was always when they kept their Paſſover; and yet this prodigious Darkneſs is witneſſed by ſeveral Heathen Writers of undoubted cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit. For the time when all this ſhould come to paſs, <hi>that Meſſiah the Prince ſhould be cut off, and to make an end of tranſgreſſion,</hi> 'tis ſo exactly ſet down in the Prophecy of Weeks in <hi>Daniel,</hi> that I may call that Prophecy a perſect Goſpel.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:106985:8"/> The very time of Lent, of faſting and mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for our ſins, is expreſly predetermined (as I may ſay) in the Prophecy of <hi>Zechariah,</hi> chap. 12. ver. 10, 11. applied by the Apoſtle directly to the paſſion of our Lord, <hi>They ſhall look upon him whom they have pierced, and they ſhall mourn for him, as one mourneth for his only Son, and ſhall be in bitterneſs for him, as one that is in bitterneſs for his firſt-born: In that day ſhall there be a great mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Jeruſalem, as the mourning of Hadadrimmon in the Valley of Megiddo:</hi> But that mourning in <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> certainly was for that excellent King <hi>Joſiah,</hi> an undoubted Type of Chriſt; And ſince it is here foretold, that the Church of Chriſt, <hi>the true Jeruſalem,</hi> ſhould ſo mourn for Chriſt as the Jews did for <hi>Joſiah,</hi> it follows for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cibly, That as the mourning for <hi>Joſiah</hi> was an annual or yearly Solemnity; ſo ours for Chriſt muſt be: and ſo is our Good-Friday, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the whole Great Week, as 'tis uſually ſtyl'd, before this Capital Feaſt in memory of his Reſurrection.</p>
            <p>As for his Reſurrection it ſelf, what Predi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction more plain and clear than the Text in the <hi>16th</hi> Pſalm, on which St. <hi>Teter</hi> made his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, <hi>Acts</hi> 2. on which St. <hi>Paul</hi> preach'd, <hi>Acts</hi> 13. <hi>Therefore my heart</hi> [Chriſts heart] <hi>was glad, and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:106985:8"/> my glory rejoyced; my fleſh alſo ſhall reſt in hope: for why? Thou ſhalt not leave my ſoul in Hell, neither ſhalt thou ſuffer thy Holy One to ſee corruption.</hi> Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever can but ſay his Creed, may in that Verſe find moſt of the prime Articles of the Chriſtian Faith, the Death and Burial of Chriſt, his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending into Hell, his riſing again from the Dead; to which if my Text be added, <hi>After two days he will revive us, in the third day he will raiſe us up;</hi> then what is wanting in this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, that we ought to believe as Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental in the Dectrine of the Reſurrection? Some indeed think themſelves moſt learned when they can ſhew theſe Prophecies literally fulfill'd in the Types of Chriſt, as this in <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> himſelf. Be it ſo; but yet ſays the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, <hi>David ſaw corruption;</hi> implying ſtrongly, that it was applicable to <hi>David</hi> in ſo poor and ſo low a ſenſe, it could hardly be ſo applied, that even according to the Letter (as we ſay) it was more truly, as well as more gloriouſly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh'd in Chriſt the Son of <hi>David.</hi> To tell you the worſt thought that can ariſe in an unbelieving heart: It has been thought by ſome, or ſaid at leaſt, That ſome Enthuſiaſtick Spirits writ theſe ſtrange things, we call the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecies of the Old Teſtament; and then ſome
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:106985:9"/> others, either as much tranſported with devout Phancies, or elſe far engaged in deſign, to ſet up a new Divinity, have adapted thoſe Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters, and alluded from theſe ſeeming Predi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions to ſuch and ſuch Paſſages in the Life and Death of Chriſt; which Paſſages either they really credited in pious ignorance, or cunningly pretended to do ſo: But if we conſider how undeniably prov'd are theſe Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Fact in the Story of Chriſt, that anſwer to thoſe Prophecies, then I hope all is firm, then the <hi>Foundation of God is ſure.</hi> Now 'tis too ſhort an expreſſion to ſay we have the ſame aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance of the truth of theſe things in the Life of Chriſt, as of any thing in the Life of <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> the Great, whoſe Victories and Monarchy were foretold, and ſhow'd him in the Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of <hi>Daniel;</hi> had we none but <hi>Quintus Curtius,</hi> and the other Heathen Writers of the Greek Story, we had reaſon enough to believe there was ſuch a Conqueror as <hi>Alexander,</hi> becauſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different perſons have recorded it, ſuch as liv'd ſo near his time, they could not be deceived, nor could they have any intereſt to deceive us; this may create a Humane Faith, that 'tis mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally impoſſible ſuch a Matter of Fact ſhould be falſe: But we have more reaſon by far to
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:106985:9"/> give credit to things atteſted by ſuch perſons as are mightily concerned and engaged by their Party to gainſay them. Now 'tis the peculiar ſtrength of the Chriſtian Faith, that two Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties which hate it moſt, I mean the Jews and the Heathens, do very ſtrongly ſupport it, and prove it againſt their Wills: For the Jews con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs and contend that ſuch Prophecies as theſe were left them, nay the moſt learned Jewiſh Doctors, Ancient and Modern, interpret moſt of theſe Prophecies to concern their Meſſiah, whom they expected to come, and to ſuffer many things, though not Death. But then our other Adverſaries, the Heathens, <hi>Celſus</hi> and <hi>Julian,</hi> and the reſt, cannot but acknowledge many of Chriſt's Miracles, though moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonably they impute them to his skill in ſome forbidden Arts: And for thoſe Miracles which they are loth to confeſs; yet they dare not deny, but his Followers dy'd to atteſt, not only their conſtancy to ſuch a belief, (for ſo have Jews and Heathens done) but to atteſt ſuch Matters of Fact as they had ſeen with their eyes, as well as ſuch Matters of <hi>Faith once delivered to the Saints;</hi> and ſuch Evidence as this, impoſſible not to be true, muſt be allow'd as ſufficient to found a <hi>Divine Faith,</hi> upon which
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:106985:10"/> 
               <hi>the Church is built,</hi> as upon a <hi>Rock,</hi> and the <hi>Gates of Hell ſhall never prevail againſt it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For, firſt, I ſuppoſe that if Chriſt wrought ſuch Miracles, and roſe from the Dead, and gave his Apoſtles like power to raiſe the Dead; then all that believe a God and his Providence, muſt admit the whole Chriſtian Faith. For Miracles, and eſpecially raiſing the Dead, are the Great Seals which God keeps in his own hands, to ſet to his Truth when he ſees occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. If the Devil himſelf were able to raiſe the Dead, why has he never done ſo, once at leaſt, after the Executioner has done his Office dextrouſly upon ſome one of his faithful Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants? He has had above 1600. Years to try, but could never ſhake Chriſtianity, as he might have done by raiſing the Dead; ſo as the act might have born the Teſt of a fair and full Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Then I ſuppoſe it poſſible for men of common ſenſe to be infallibly ſure of ſome notable and very remarkable Matter of Fact, which they all believe, and think that they ſee with their eyes, and hear with their ears, and their hands handle at the ſame time. For if we cannot be ſure of ſo much as this comes to, then we may all be dead men, or no men, but
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:106985:10"/> beaſts, for any thing we can diſcern: But if we can be certain of thus much, then we muſt allow it as poſſible for thoſe who pretended to have ſeen Chriſt raiſed from the Dead, to be as infallibly certain that they were not miſtaken.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, I ſuppoſe it very poſſible for ſome Matter of Fact that was not ſeen with ones own eyes, (ſuppoſe it be done in the next room) to be ſo undeniably witneſſed, as ſhall abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly ſupply the want of ocular demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, I aſſume, That if we can be ſure of any Matter of Fact which we did not ſee with our own eyes, then we may be infinitely ſurer of the wonderful Works of Chriſt, and eſpecially of his Glorious Reſurrection; That Chriſt was openly crucified, or nailed to a Croſs before a multitude of Enemies; That af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter exquiſite pains, he gave up the Ghoſt; Then to make all ſure, That he was thruſt into the vital parts, that the water guſh'd out of his ſide; without which Cooler he muſt needs have been parch'd to death, if he had not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergone many deaths before: that the Apoſtle St. <hi>John,</hi> who ſaw this, with many others <hi>bare record;</hi> That <hi>their record is true;</hi> That the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies of Chriſtianity knew it to be ſo uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troulably
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:106985:11"/> true (as to the point of this Dying) that ſcarce any Jew or Heathen has ever been ſo impudent as to deny the certainty of his Death; That this extraordinary Perſon, ſo pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly executed, was cloſed and ſealed up in a Sepulchre, and his Body guarded by Orders thus ſtrictly iſſued forth, <hi>Ye have a Watch, go make it as ſure as you can;</hi> That after three days he appeared alive again in the ſame Body; That he appeared ſeveral times, in divers places, to many Spectators at once, to above five hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Perſons; That he had threatned his Foes beforehand, that he would unbar the Gates of Death, let them do what they could to debar or hinder him; for it was their own Depoſition before <hi>Pontius Pilate</hi> himſelf, <hi>Sir, we remember that this Deceiver ſaid while he lived, The third day I will riſe again:</hi> That he provok'd ſome that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved not for joy, and ſome that obſtinately disbelieved, to feel his Pulſe, to <hi>handle and ſee the print of the nails,</hi> and <hi>to thruſt their hands into his ſide,</hi> till the moſt incredulous man aſſented whether he would or no; Theſe Matters of Fact were immediately proclaim'd and preach'd to all the World, by ſuch Eye-Witneſſes every where, as not only were ready to ſeal it with their bloud, That this Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:106985:11"/> of theirs was true; but God alſo ſet to his Seal, That many of thoſe who were ready thus to lay down their lives, and who took it upon their deaths, that they ſaw Chriſt raiſed from the Dead, ſhould themſelves be enabled to work undeniable Miracles, and even to raiſe the Dead. No wonder then if the Goſpel ſpread ſo faſt: For if a man of God (how con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible ſoever) ſhould revive but one Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factor after he had been openly put to death, it would not be many Months e're the whole World would have an account of it.</p>
            <p>But then their working of Miracles, as a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration that their Witneſs was moſt true, who affirmed they had ſeen Chriſt riſen, comes to be as unqueſtionably aſſerted by many other Eye-Witneſſes, and by ſo many others that had it from the mouths of theſe, they made up a No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Army of Martyrs, who lov'd not their lives in compariſon of this Truth which they ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanc'd by their deaths, <hi>viz.</hi> That they had ſeen the Apoſtles or Apoſtolical men <hi>confirming the Word, by Signs following.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And laſtly, That there were ſuch a Glorious Company of Martyrs, ſuch as endured a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand indignities, (and, as it were, died <hi>often)</hi> with this Teſtimony of Jeſus in their mouths, this
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:106985:12"/> Teſtimony (I ſay) of the Martyrs is confeſs'd and acknowledged by all the adverſe Parties; no Jew, no Pagan, no Perſecutor of Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, no Atheiſt, no Devil, had ever the hardineſs to deny what themſelves had inflicted, and for what theſe men had ſuffered. And all this put together were enough, one would think, to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure the Doctrine of the Reſurrection, and by conſequence the Chriſtian Faith.</p>
            <p>No, It is ſaid, That one man may poſſibly deceive, or be deceived: If one, then two, then three, then thirty, then thirty thouſand, then all the whole Company of Martyrs. Truly 'tis extremely hard to conceive, that in things ſo groſs and palpable, and of higheſt conſequence, any one man of common ſence could be impos'd upon, much leſs deceitfully impoſe on others, and thoſe that were deareſt to him, where he could have no imaginable intereſt to do ſo, as it was in this Caſe of the Primitive martyr'd Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>But what if humane Nature might admit of this higheſt depravation of ſence and reaſon in one ſingle Example? What if an Heap of Corn being poured out at randome on a large Threſhing-Floor, it may happen after many tryals that ſome of the Grains may fall into
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:106985:12"/> ſome regular Figure; would it follow thence that this whole World of Beauty and Order could have been compoſed by a caſual motion of Atoms? What if a Printers Characters be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thrown together at all adventures, it may come to paſs after ten hundred thouſand eſſays, that ſuch of the Letters may accidentally meet as may make up the two or three firſt words of my Text; yet could it enter into the heart of man to think it poſſible for them ſo to be join<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by mere chance, as to make up all this Divine Prophecy of <hi>Hoſea?</hi> or (to put the Caſe yet higher) to make up all the Sacred Volumes of the Old and New Teſtament? To cut the matter ſhort: Can Chance produce effects as wiſe as any, God can produce? But if all rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon abhors the Atheiſt's wild ſuppoſition, That ſuch blind Cauſes, as an Heap of Corn, or a Printers Letters, that have no greater tendency one way than another, ſhould produce effects ſo extravagantly wiſe by Chance only; then if we follow the Grain of the ſame Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and purſue it home, it runs more clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and ends in a more infallible Concluſion, againſt the Deiſts (as they love to ſtyle them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves) or the Disbelievers of the Reſurrection and Chriſtianity, than againſt the Atheiſts.
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:106985:13"/> For that a World of knowing and rational Beings, or Men, at leaſt, of common ſenſe, that have a natural appetite, an inſeparable in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination to their own happineſs, (which thoſe inanimate things have not) that all of them could act ſo extreme unnaturally in an Affair that concerned all their good in this life, as well as in the next, as all of them wilfully to deceive the Children of their own Bowels; or all of them to be ſo ſenſeleſly negligent, as to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer themſelves to be perpetually abuſed, when they needed but open their eyes to diſcover the impoſture, if there had been any in theſe Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Fact: this is utterly impoſſible to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, and is really beyond the reach of all ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination. If it be poſſible (I ſay <hi>but if</hi> ſtill) if it be poſſible for any very conſidering man to debauch his Reaſon into a real disbelief of the Reſurrection, and of thoſe things which <hi>are moſt ſurely believed among us,</hi> and upon <hi>many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible Proofs</hi> (as St. <hi>Luke</hi> declares) that man can have no reaſon in the world to conclude there is any thing real: nay, all the reaſon he has left will rather oblige him to ſit down under a wild ſuſpicion that his Life is a waking Dream, that the Heaven and the Earth and all things elſe about him, are but falſe repreſentations
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:106985:13"/> made by ſome hidden accurſed power that is always deluding his fancy, and that there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in the World but the Devil and himſelf fit Companions for one another.</p>
            <p>And having thus diſcours'd Hiſtorically of the Matter of Fact which the Prophet delivers in the Text, I ſhall now proceed to conſider but very briefly of the Myſtery of Faith, the conſequence or effect of theſe great things that Chriſt either did or ſuffered for us; ſo <hi>the power of his Reſurrection</hi> (as St. <hi>Paul</hi> calls it) is alſo ſet down in theſe words, <hi>He ſhall revive us. He ſhall raiſe us up again, and we ſhall live in his ſight; He ſhall come unto us as the rain, as the latter and former rain unto the earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Similitude is taken from a thing that is moſt common, that is, <hi>Rain;</hi> and yet this Philoſophical, or at leaſt this Experimental Age will allow me thus much, That the rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Notes, and the moſt undoubted Concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, in the Book of Nature, are ſuch as we draw from the moſt vulgar, and therefore the moſt conſtant Obſervations. Therefore of all the Similitudes upon which the Divine Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies and Parables in the Old and New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment are turn'd and form'd, there are no Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſons ſo frequently uſed as theſe, between
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:106985:14"/> the products of Nature, and the growth of Grace; between the Fruits of the Earth, and the encreaſe of heavenly Vertue and Glory in the humane Soul and Body: no temporal Bleſſings are ſo often promis'd, or ſo conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perform'd, to put us in mind of the Spiritual, as <hi>the ſending of the former and the latter rain, the ſhining of the Sun on the juſt and on the unjuſt; the watering the earth, and bleſſing it, and making it very plenteous.</hi> The Church is every where repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented as God's Husbandry, as God's Vineyard; and Chriſt himſelf is by himſelf reſembled to <hi>a Corn of Wheat that fell into the Ground, and dy'd;</hi> as if he had ſaid, <hi>The Corn of Wheat, this my Body; the Corn of Wheat which falls into the ground, and dies, this is my Body, which is given and broken for you.</hi> To the ſame intent and purpoſe 'tis obſervable, that the Ceremony <hi>of waving the Sheaf</hi> of the firſt-fruit of the Harveſt, on the next day after the Feaſt of the Paſſoever, was appointed in the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> as a ſignificant Type of the Reſurrection, or of Chriſt's revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and <hi>raiſing</hi> our mortal Bodies as <hi>His Sheaves</hi> with him; and 'tis yet more obſervable, that God's peculiar Providence over-ruling the blind Jews to defer their Feaſt until Saturday, that year when our Saviour ſuffered, order'd it ſo,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:106985:14"/> that they <hi>wav'd the Sheaf</hi> exactly on the firſt Eaſter-morning when Chriſt aroſe.</p>
            <p>But theſe effects on our Bodies are not the only or the greateſt effects of Chriſt's Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection; the Power and Wiſdom of God in it is greater ſtill, in compariſon of this <hi>Wiſdom</hi> the Apoſtle <hi>counted all things no better than dung;</hi> good only, as that is, to manure the Ground, to prepare it for that good Seed, and for this bleſſed Rain that ſhould come upon it; that was all that all the knowledge of the World was good for to thoſe who knew not Chriſt: But of what conſequence now to our Souls, as well as our Bodies, is the Knowledge and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of this prime Fundamental Article? The ſumm of all this, Becauſe Chriſt did and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered all this for us, therefore did God his Father give him by the Holy Spirit a power to raiſe up himſelf firſt, and then all that are <hi>his,</hi> with all manner of Reſurrections both of Soul and Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, from all manner of Deaths to which they were obnoxious. Therefore the Scripture in ſome places uſes the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, <hi>his full and intire Reſurrectim;</hi> the whole <hi>6th</hi> of the Romans, and moſt of the <hi>5th,</hi> is upon the force of his Paſſion and his Reſurrection, where 'tis made the Idaeal Cauſe, the very ſimilitude
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:106985:15"/> and pattern of our Reſurrection, and, more than ſo, a vital influence is ſuppoſed to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived from him upon us, to aſſimilate or make us like him, as well in our Souls as our Bodies; <hi>that as we have been planted together in the likeneſs of his Death, we ſhall be alſo in the likeneſs of his Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection:</hi> For this implanting, <hi>viz.</hi> in our Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſm, ſuppoſes a drawing of Vertue from Chriſt, and is ſecur'd on his part to our lives end, there is imply'd not only our Obligation, but our Ability, by the power he gives us, that we alſo <hi>ſhould walk</hi> as he did after this day <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty days</hi> together <hi>in newneſs of life;</hi> ſuppoſing that none can raiſe their hearts from the World, and be thus renewed, but by <hi>thinking on theſe things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this falls in with my third and laſt Part, the Obligation upon our parts, or the Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on impoſed upon us, if we mean to reap ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage from this revealed Doctrine of Chriſt's Reſurrection and ours; then muſt theſe Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples be purſued extreamly home, and we muſt go on throughout the whole courſe of our lives to practiſe accordingly, <hi>Then ſhall we know, if we follow on to know the Lord?</hi> For in the very next words to thoſe of my Text, the Prophet takes up this lamentation, <hi>O Ephraim, what ſhall
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:106985:15"/> I do unto thee? O Judah, what ſhall I do unto thee? For your goodneſs is as a morning cloud, and as the early dew it goeth away.</hi> It ſeems that theſe men whom the Prophet had to do with, were men of good intentions; but ſo they ſay, Hell it ſelf is full of good intentions, that is, 'tis full of thoſe that one time or other intended to do well: but here was their great miſtake, they thought the great work was done as ſoon as it was but intended. Alas! we are apt to take every faint endeavour and every feeble attempt for <hi>overcoming the World.</hi> But <hi>then ſhall we know, if we follow on to know the Lord;</hi> that is, if we proceed in taking juſt pains with our ſelves, till we <hi>love</hi> what we <hi>know,</hi> or elſe we <hi>know no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing yet as we ought to know; He that loveth not, knoweth not God; for God is love; That Jeſus Chriſt came into the World to ſave Sinners,</hi> this is not only <hi>a faithful ſaying,</hi> but avowed with good reaſon by the Apoſtle <hi>to be worthy of all men to be received;</hi> but every thing in Nature is received according to the capacity and figure of the worthy or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy Receiver. Our Chriſtian Philoſophy! 'tis a moſt noble ſpeculation! Angels delight to pry into it! Unbelievers themſelves will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge in their ſober moods, that our main Body of Divinity is a piece of magnificent
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:106985:16"/> Wit, admirably refin'd, and ſtrongly knit to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether: But becauſe they want a ſoul for it, to ponder and contemplate theſe great and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazing Truths, till they come to practiſe as they ought; therefore the <hi>men love darkneſs rather than light,</hi> not that Religion has any blind ſides in it, <hi>for God is light, and in him is no darkneſs at all,</hi> but <hi>becauſe their deeds are evil,</hi> and <hi>every one that doth evil hates the light.</hi> One of themſelves, a great one, has confeſs'd the only reaſon why men have ſo little controverted or contradicted the Principles of ſome other Sciences, by which we build Houſes or meaſure Fields, 'tis becauſe (ſays he) theſe Principles do not croſs our Appetites: Be that famous Propoſition in <hi>Euclid</hi> true or falſe, for which <hi>Pythagoras</hi> offered an hundred Oxen in thanks to Heaven for help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him to find and demonſtrate it, they need not ſacrifice one vile affection for it; and yet e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven thoſe Principles that are as plain as two and two is four, have been gainſaid: But then it was for ſome intereſt; it was in hopes of founding a ſpeculative Atheiſm (for the ſake of a practical one you may be ſure; of found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, I ſay) more ſtrongly upon Scepticiſm, to the utter contempt of humane Nature; baf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fling all ſenſe and reaſon, granting juſt nothing
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:106985:16"/> for fear of allowing ſome truth, leſt then ſome Notions of good and evil ſhould have follow'd upon it. But to ſhew 'tis the inordination of mens affections that cauſes <hi>the evil heart of unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief to depart from the living God,</hi> inſtead <hi>of follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on to know the Lord:</hi> What was it elſe but the <hi>old leven of the Phariſees and of the Sadduces,</hi> that converted Chriſts Manna into Gall? that turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>the very Bread that came down from Heaven</hi> into that <hi>which periſh'd with them?</hi> For when the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſaw him <hi>multiply the Loaves,</hi> they were ready to follow him for thoſe; not only to ſatisfie their hunger, but their ambition: for preſently they apprehended he that was able to make ſuch extemporary proviſion for a multitude, had it in his power to maintain and defray an Army upon eaſie terms. Whereupon 'tis very obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable in the next Chapter, after the relation of this Miracle, <hi>they would have taken him by force to make him King;</hi> intending him, no queſtion, for their General againſt the Romans that op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd them; ſo that he was fain to avoid their irreſiſtible importunities of accepting a Crown, by <hi>retiring up into a Mountain with his Diſciples:</hi> But when they ſaw him reſolv'd to be a man of retirement, when they ſaw him bent upon it, not to ſerve turns and their politick Ends, not
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:106985:17"/> to head their rebellious deſigns againſt their Roman Maſters, nor to cheriſh their aſpiring thoughts for Univerſal Monarchy; then <hi>ſay we not well, That thou art a Samaritan, and haſt a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil?</hi> But after all the dirt and contempt they had thrown upon him; yet if at any time they took a fancy from ſome powerful action of his, that he was breaking out in a blaze of State and Splendor, ſtraight they began again to worſhip him as the riſing Sun, then they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſounded <hi>Hoſannabs, Bleſſed be the King that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in the name of the Lord;</hi> then He was <hi>the Son of David,</hi> and <hi>Meſſiah the Prince,</hi> the Heir of the Crown, while they had any hopes and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctations that <hi>the Kingdom of God</hi> (as they call'd it) <hi>ſhould immediately appear.</hi> But then again when they found themſelves diſappointed by his repeated Declarations, That <hi>his Kingdom was not of this World,</hi> they ſoon return'd to their old paſs, <hi>We have no King but Caeſar,</hi> He that <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth himſelf a King</hi> (when they would have made him ſo) <hi>ſpeaketh againſt Caeſar:</hi> Nay, to inſtance in better men; His own Diſciples themſelves, till the Deſcent of the Holy Spirit upon them had ſubdued their affections, they were but <hi>men of like affections with us,</hi> their paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions clouded their reaſon, they had ſome ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:106985:17"/> doubtings and failings too, they deſerv'd ſometimes to be cenſured by their Great Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter and ours for <hi>men</hi> of but <hi>little faith.</hi> But all their want of affiance proceeded not from want of evidence in the thing it ſelf, <hi>That which we have heard, which we have ſeen with our eyes, which we have lookt upon, and our hands have handled of the Word of Life, that which we have ſeen and heard, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare we unto you:</hi> Did theſe good men want Proofs of the Reſurrection? It was proved to all their ſenſes, and <hi>yet ſome doubted;</hi> becauſe they did not ſee him in a triumphal Chariot: for to the laſt hour of his ſtay upon Earth, and immediately before his aſcenſion into Heaven, they never loſt that ambition, which made them ſay, <hi>Wilt thou at this time reſtore again the Kingdom unto Iſrael?</hi> But the former Conteſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong themſelves which of them ſhould be the greateſt, had like to have made St. <hi>Peter</hi> himſelf no Chriſtian; as thoſe that call themſelves the Succeſſors of St. <hi>Peter</hi> have almoſt turn'd the Chriſtian World upſide down with the ſame unhappy Conteſt about Supremacy, ſo early begun in the Church, they forget what a ſharp rebuke it brought upon St. <hi>Peter, Get thee behind me Satan;</hi> for he tempted our Saviour, as did the Devil before him, to think <hi>of the Kingdoms
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:106985:18"/> of this World, and the Glories of them,</hi> rather than ſpeak of ſuffering at <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> for which his Maſter gave him fair warning to look to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and his own deceitful heart, <hi>For thou ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voureſt not the things of God, but thoſe that are of men.</hi> 'Tis ſtill the ſcandal they take at the Doctrine <hi>of the Croſs</hi> of Chriſt, or rather at the Duty of <hi>taking up the Croſs</hi> themſelves, that hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders the whole Jewiſh Nation, which knows ſo much of theſe Prophecies, from <hi>following on to know the Lord.</hi> But it was on the other ſide a very remarkable Proof, that <hi>they who do his will ſhall know of his Doctrine,</hi> that when the Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees, with their overweening pride and ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſtood out againſt all conviction that Chriſt himſelf could afford them, when the Sadduces deny'd the Immortality of the Soul, becauſe they rather wiſh'd the Immortality of the Body and its fleſhly Luſts; the <hi>Eſſenes,</hi> another Sect among the Jews, whom we do not find any where reprehended by our Saviour; for they were honeſt and humble men of heart, they liv'd much within themſelves, and had little to do with the World; theſe flock'd apace into the Church, (as the Church-Hiſtories inform us) and, for <hi>receiving the good Seed,</hi> theſe proved the beſt Ground in all the Land of Promiſe.
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:106985:18"/> The Sower, that is, the Preacher, could he be ſure he were enter'd upon ſuch Ground, he might afford to do as <hi>Moſes</hi> was bidden to do, and <hi>put off his ſhoes from his feet</hi> in reverence to it; Who is there that would not willingly go barefoot all the days of his life, on conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the place whereon he took his ſtanding were always ſuch holy Ground? But how ſhall we become ſuch? My Anſwer is ſtill the ſame, <hi>Then ſhall we know, if we follow on to know the Lord;</hi> and our Saviour himſelf has told us, <hi>That the good ground are they which in an honeſt and good heart, having heard the Word, keep it, and bring forth fruit with patience.</hi> Which that we may all do, I ſhall conclude with the Apoſtle's excellent Prayer: <hi>Now the God of peace, who did bring again from the dead the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, the great Shepherd of the Sheep, through the blood of the everlaſting Teſtament, make us perfect in every good work to do his will, working in us that which is well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing in his ſight, through Jeſus Chriſt, to whom be Glory for ever and ever.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
